Faisal Taher

51 Butterwick Fields, Horwich, BL65GY

faisalt@gmail.com, http://www.faisaltaher.com, +44 07854314890

Skills Summary

Languages C#, Python, JavaScript, PHP, Java.

Markup and Query HTML5, CSS3, SQL.

UX Techniques User journeys, storyboarding, user testing, interviewing, personas and

scenarios, surveys, wireframing.

Frameworks and Tools Node.js, JQuery, Django, Docker, Backbone.js, .NET, Flask, Jekyll,

Sentry, Git, REST, unit testing, MSTest, coverage reports.

Prototyping and Design Balsamiq, Photoshop, Illustrator, Fusion 360, concept sketching,

Raspberry Pi, 3D printing, laser-cutting, Arduino.

User Testing and Data

Analysis

Highly experienced in planning and running user testing sessions and integrating the results into the development lifecycle. This includes conducting interviews, running workshops, setting up data capture,

and performing qualitative and quantitative analysis.

Adaptability Adapted to new challenging roles and responsibilities including:

working in an agile team and developing software across the stack, providing consultancy and liaising with clients from different

backgrounds, learning new techniques and technologies to build novel real-world interfaces, and writing and presenting top-level research.

Work Experience

Senior Inventor, Hardy & Ellis Inventions Ltd

January 2016 – present

- Engage in agile methods including stand-ups, ticket allocation (Trello), pair coding,
 brainstorming sessions, and design and engineering planning. Recently ran a retrospective on a project that led to improved communication and useful design processes.
- Proactive in the product development lifecycle, including milestone planning, requirements gathering, brainstorming ideas, writing test-driven front-end and back-end applications that are run through CI/CD pipelines, writing documentation, and maintaining deployments.
- Follow a strong philosophy of UX and user needs when designing applications. This includes conducting discovery phase research, producing user journeys and interface mockups, ensuring cross platform compatibility, and developing interfaces that are useful and usable.
- Recently completed and deployed a series of interactive installations (based on a distributed system architecture) at an innovation centre, which is currently hosting tours.
- Captured a client's vision for an interactive room application through hands-on involvement in all areas of development, including: running a requirements workshop, producing user journeys, creating interface designs, writing robust code, and developing a website to host user documentation. This led to several deployments across the UK.

Research Associate, Lancaster University

November 2013 - June 2016

- Worked with emerging physical shape-changing display prototypes and applied multidisciplinary knowledge (e.g. interaction design, user research, software engineering).
- Led a large-scale project with a team from multiple European institutions that involved building software and hardware components for, as well as evaluating, a physical bar chart.
 The project led to top-tier international conference publications and BBC news coverage.

Designed and ran several user testing sessions to evaluate user behaviours and interaction preferences. I designed questionnaires, tasks, and interviews, set up recording equipment, and engaged with participants.

Software Development Contractor, under contract to May 2013 – December 2013 St Andrews Engineering Ltd

- Designed, developed, and deployed a business management system that enabled enquiry management, quotes and purchase order generation, and timesheet logging.
- Engaged in regular meetings with various company stakeholders to review milestones.

Technical Project Consultant, Knowledge Business

March 2011 – April 2013

Centre, Unite with Business, Lancaster University

- Wrote business management applications that aided the growth of SMEs.
- Built strong communication skills by liaising with a diverse range of clients, including engineers, developers, designers, and a magazine editor.
- Formulated clear sets of requirements, produced documentation, and provided technical guidance following project completions.

Web Developer, Backbone IT Group

January 2012 – December 2012

- Designed and improved the usability of client websites, including showcasing and ecommerce websites.
- Developed a web application that enabled the company administrators and its clients to manage transactions on their partner online shops.

Education

PhD Computer Science Indoor Navigation Systems

Degree awarded Lancaster University 2008 to 2013

- Developed and deployed a prototype indoor navigation system for mobile phones and public displays. The system integrated 3D visualizations, digital maps and signage, as well as sensor technologies such as NFC and QR codes for location information.
- Conducted a number of user evaluations with the navigation system to explore interaction requirements and published/presented several international conference papers.

Masters by Research

Human-Computer Interaction

Degree awarded with distinction Lancaster University 2007 to 2008

- Collaborated in an innovative design project to develop a virtual usability testing laboratory using Second Life.
- Dissertation: Developed and evaluated an indoor navigation system that later formed part of my PhD research.

Bachelor of Science (Hons)

Degree awarded Lancaster University 2004 to 2007

Computer Science with Multimedia Systems

- Included modules based on programming, networking, digital media standards, database systems, algorithms, operating systems, and the software development lifecycle.
- Dissertation: Investigating wayfinding in virtual 3D environments.

Interests and Hobbies

I enjoy reading science-fiction novels, digital photography, drawing comics, cooking, going to the gym, and taking part in running events.